Guide to the Charles N. Hunter Papers, 1850s-1932 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Personal and Professional Papers Series, 1861-1931 and undated, (7 boxes)
  - Other Professional Papers Subseries, 1850s-1931 and undated
    - Three news articles from The North Carolina Review, 1920s: "Petition of Josiah Turner: Remarkable Letter of Eccentric Character Asking the Benefit of Johnson's Amnesty Proclamation" (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Three news articles from The North Carolina Review, 1920s: "A Noteworthy Publication: A Comprehensive History of Political, Social, Economic, and Intellectual Life of the Southern People" (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Application for First Mortgage Trust Fund Certificate to the Reserve Deposit Company, circa 1920s (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - "A Thousand Arms," a handwritten article on the commencement address at Shaw University, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - "Negro Migration," editorial review from The Missionary Voice, 1921 March (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Articles of Copartnership between Charles N. Hunter and J. H. Love, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - "A Bill to be Entitled an Act to Place the Name of Jane Roberson on the Pension Roll," 1921 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Historical sketch of the George M. Horton Public School, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Graded test of M. Brown, 1924 July 14 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Principal's final report of Wilson Mills, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Principal's Monthly Report of Wilson Mills, 1926 April (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Receipt of gift from Library Committee of the University of Pennsylvania, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - N.C. Industrial Association Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1930 June 19 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - The Great Negro State Fair list of funding sources, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Contract between N.C. Industrial Association and the Wake County Fair Association, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Description of agreement between N.C. Industrial Association and the Wake County Fair Association, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Secretary's Report of the N.C. Industrial Association, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - List of Ladies' Committee for the Fair, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - N.C. Industrial Association Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1931 June 25 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - "Governor Jarvis Recommends the Annual Appropriation of $500,000," 1931 May 30 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - N.C. Industrial Association Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1931 June 17 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements of the N.C. Negro State Fair, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Address by Hunter on Negro Autonomy, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Description of North Carolina Industrial Association, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Objectives of the N.C. Industrial Association, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Historical account of the N.C. Industrial Association, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - "Business before the committee," 1930 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Articles of Arguments, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Constitution of the N.C. Industrial Association, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Stock letter informing Hunter of appointment to N.C. Industrial Association Executive Committee, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Call for a meeting of the Executive Committee of the N.C. Industrial Association, 1930 June 7 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Receipts, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - List of receipts for the N.C. Negro State Fair, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Nametag (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letter from T. S. Inbordon, then-president of N.C. Industrial Association (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Notes with numbers and tally marks (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letter from Locke Craig (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Postcard from Q. W. Cochran (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - List of pupils and payments (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Declaration of committee establishment (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Poem (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Test (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Invitation to Commencement Week exercises of St. Augustine School (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - John H. Williamson's Salary Account (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - School's rules (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Biographical sketch of Charles N. Hunter (handwritten and typed copies) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Dictionary of North Carolina biographical sketch of Charles N. Hunter (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Minutes of meeting of "colored voters and taxpayers," Raleigh, NC, Oct. 17 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "Negroes Have Taken Marked Steps Foward Along Essential Courses," Raleigh Times (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Two newspaper articles from unknown source (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Receipt from the F. M. Paist Company of Philadelphia (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Report of Work for May (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "Outline of Plan for State-wide Activity in Training Teachers for Industrial Work in Colored Schools" (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "To Students of Colored Colleges and Universities' (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - List of the South Carolina State Board of Education members (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "Statement on Present Conditions by the A.M.E. Preachers' Meeting of Norfolk, Virginia" (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Newspaper clippings announcing the transfer of real estate (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Colonel George T. Wassom photograph (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - "Causes and Prevention of Consumption" issued by the North Carolina Board of Health (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - "Mr. Gosney's Position" (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - "Big Dinner for Former Slaves: Let Everybody Help - Send in Your Contributions" (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Note regarding the updating of life insurance benefits (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Agenda for group meeting (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Stock letter appealing for voters to keep the State Fair in Raleigh (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - "Which Shall It Be - Foreign or Negro Labor?" (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - "Class History" (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Test questions (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - "Wilson Chapel Methodist Episcopal Church, Oberlin Village" (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Activities of Shop 80 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - "A Dry Yard" (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Chapter 8 test (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - "Mr. Otey's Oration" (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Grand Concert program of the Berry O'Kelly School (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - List of volunteers (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Notes for Easter Service (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Bills Payable (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Ladies' Committee for the N.C. State Fair (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - La Dainty and J&T Lines advertisement (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - "The Voice of Free Grace" sheet music (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - List of farmers and prices awarded at fair (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - List of persons and monetary amounts (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - "Secured subscriptions" (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1869-1930 and undated
    Contains a varied assemblage of lectures, addresses, reports, biographical sketches, obituaries, and other compositions, chiefly written by Charles Hunter. Unless otherwise indicated, the author is Hunter. When possible, original titles are transcribed and dates are given. Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - "Address on the Presentation of the Portrait of Professor J. H. Branch to the Washington School," 1916 May 31 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - "Address to the Young Men's Christian Association by Prof. Chas. N. Hunter: What Do We Believe?" (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - "Afro-American Schools in Raleigh" (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - "The Berry O'Kelly Training and Industrial School" (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - "Biographical Sketch of Rev. Lewis Perry" (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - "Bishop A. N. Wayman" (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - "Business Enterprises Among Negroes in Raleigh" (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Celebration of Emancipation Day Speeches, 1895, 1899, 1912, 1923 and undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - "A Card to the Voters of the Eastern Ward," 1874 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Composition book with letters to editors, poetry, and lists of names, 1869-1872 and undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - "Congregationalism Among the Colored people of North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - "Reverend A. G. Davis" (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - "Death of General Grant," 1885 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - "Professor W. F. Debnam" (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - "Professor Henry Beard Delaney" (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - "Do The Negroes of Raleigh Repudiate the Proclamation of Emancipation?" (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - "East Raleigh School-Second Session, 1879-1880" (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - "Education in North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - "Essentials of True Greatness: Address by C. N. Hunter on the occasion of the celebration of the 30th Anniversary of the service of Rev. R. H. W. Leak, D.D. in the ministry of the A.M.E. Church" (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - "Fellow Workers" (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - "Freedom is Man's Birth Right" (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - "The Future of the Negro" (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - "Grecian Mythology" (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - "The Growth of Slavery in the Colonies" (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - "I Was Born A Slave" (excerpt) (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - "A Great White Southerner's Tribute to a Great Negro: The John O'Daniel Hosiery Mill of Durham, N.C. - General Julian S. Carr thus honors his trusted employees" (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - "History of Education in North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - "A Historical Sketch," L. M. Mason (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - "Charles Wesley Hoover" (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - "Edward Hughes Hunter" (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - "George M. Horton: Historical Sketches No. 1" (3 copies) (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - "History of John Chavis: The Negro Scholar, Preacher and Teacher" (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "Lernual Battle Hinton" (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - "Incidents of Slave Life" (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - "Jesus" (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - "Ea. Johnson, LLB." (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - "James H. Jones" (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - "Jones School" (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - "Liberty" (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - "Norfleet Jeffries" (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Incomplete Works (1 folder) (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Letters to the Editor (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - "Macedonia" (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - "Memorial of Professor J. H. Branch," 1916 Jan. 7 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - "Memorial of J. N. Kirby," 1903 May 17 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - "Moses the Leader" (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - "My Creed" (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - "My Recollections" (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - "The National Freedman's Savings and Trust Company" (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - "The Negro Does Not Want 'Social Equality': Capt. Ashe Recalls Important Negro History" (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - "The Negro in 1884" (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - "Negro Progress in North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - "The Negro's Call to World Service" (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - "The Negroes' Position" (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - "The New States" (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - "The North Carolina Institution for the Deaf, Dumb, and Blind, Colored Department" (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - "On the Death of C.N. Otey" (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - "Opportunities and Possibilities of the Protestant Episcopal Church among the Negroes" (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - "Oration of the late Frederick Douglas [Douglass] preserved by the late Chas. N. Hunter to whom the manuscript was given," 1872 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - "Petition" (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - "Pleads for the Negro and for Justice" (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - "Possibilities" (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - "Progress of the Negro Race in North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - "Progress of the Negroes of North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - "The Race Problem in America - A Call to Christian Courage" (2 letters) (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - "Report of the Grand Worthy Secretary to the Officers and members of the Grand Lodge of North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - "Report on Freedmen's Address" (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - "Review of Negro Life in North Carolina with My Recollections" (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - "Professor N.A. Roberts, D.D." (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - "Rome was not Built in a Day" (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - "Dawson Andrew Scruggs" (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - "Sifting or the Ministration of Adversity" (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - "Some of the Evils of Reconstruction" (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - "Special Arrangements for White People" (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - "St. Augustine Normal School and Collegiate Institute" (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - "St. Augustine Protestant Episocpal Church" (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - "Steps in Reading" (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - "The Story of John Chavis" (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - "The Teaching of Spelling in our Schools" (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - "To the Colored People of North Carolina" (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - "To the Negro Voters of the State of North Carolina," 1928 (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - "To the People of North Carolina," 1910 (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - "Total Abstinence" (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - "Trend of Slavery toward the Sonnet" (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Untitled Addresses (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Topics include a brief history of the North Carolina Negro State Fair and funding for the Berry O'Kelly School. Other speeches feature historical facts of Raleigh and topics of racial uplift. Speeches addressed to the Constitutional Convention of North Carolina, the North Carolina legislature, local schools and school systems, members of the Howard Band of Hope, the Union Brothers and Victor Fire Company, the National Negro Business League, and the Right Worthy Grand Ledge of North Carolina among others.
    - Untitled Work (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Untitled essays cover African American history nationally, in the South, and in North Carolina.
    - "What Do We Believe?" (5 copies) (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "What Next?" (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "What of the Negro State Fair - Shall We Go to Some Other City?" (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - "What Shall the Negro Do?" (3 copies) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - "A Word of Caution and Encouragement to the Negro" (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Scrapbooks Series, 1866-1932 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Seventeen scrapbooks containing clippings and other items concerning race relations and other social, political, and economic affairs pertaining to African Americans. Assembled by Charles Hunter, they were taken chiefly from newspapers published in North Carolina, but their scope is national as well as regional and local. A wide range of topics and views are represented in the clippings, which include editorials from across the political spectrum (including both views with which Hunter was likely sympathetic and some with which he almost certainly was not); news articles about criminal accusations against African Americans and the lynchings and mob violence that often followed; accounts of North Carolina Negro State Fairs and various exhibitions and events for and about African Americans; articles describing the opening ceremonies and commencement speeches at African American high-schools and colleges; a number of articles and letters to the editor written by Charles N. Hunter himself, generally expressing his views on race relations; many articles about local, state, and national politics, particularly concerning the role of African Americans in state and national politics (and especially focusing on the disenfranchisement of African Americans in Southern states); and various religious, inspirational, and motivational texts - along with a great deal of other material relating to the African American experience at the turn of the 20th century.
  The original scrapbooks have been disbound and photocopies have been made of all the clippings. The copies have been arranged chronologically for ease of use. Copies of the indices to the original scrapbooks - detailing the arrangement of the clippings in their original context - have also been retained.
  Many of the clippings were pasted onto ledger sheets that had previously been used for Hunter's school and financial records. Some pages of these records were still intact and legible. These records have also been preserved and are included in this series. The news clippings date from 1866-1932 (with some undated entries organized by topic); the financial and school records to which they were pasted date from 1886-1913.
  - Scrapbooks: Use Copies
    Photocopies of the pages of clippings from Hunter's scrapbooks. Whenever possible, these copies should be used instead of the originals.
    - Scrapbook pages, 1866-1907 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook pages, 1908-1932 (Box 8)
    - Undated clippings: inspirational/religious
    - Undated clippings: news and editorials
    - Undated clippings: poetry
    - Indices to the original volumes
  - Scrapbooks: Originals
    The original pages from Hunter's disbound scrapbooks.
    [Access RESTRICTED due to fragile nature. Use copies available in boxes 7-8.]
    - School and Financial Records, 1886-1913 and undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Scrapbook, original binding (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Scrapbook, 1886-1921 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1886-1921 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1891-1928 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1867-1928 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Scapbook, 1871-1928 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Scapbook, 1871-1928 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Scapbook, 1871-1928 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1875-1924 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook, 1875-1924 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1875-1924 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1877-1924 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1877-1924 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1882-unknown (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1882-unknown (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbook, 1879-1888 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1885-1929 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook, 1885-1929 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook, 1885-1929 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1871-1928 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1891-1911 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook, 1891-1911 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Scrapbook, various dates (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook, various dates (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, various dates (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, various dates (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, various dates (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook, various dates (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbook, 1902-1927 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1902-1927 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook, 1902-1927 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook, 1867 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1887-1929 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1887-1929 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook, 1887-1928 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Scrapbook, 1887-1928 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Scrapbook, 1887-1928 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Scrapbook, 1888-1905 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1924 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1924 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1924 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1924 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1924 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1924 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Emancipation Celebration, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Christian Poems, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)